Oscar Bluemner
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
- Annotated Books & Catalogs, 1907-1933, Series 5:; (Box 4-5; 1.0 linear feet)
  - Annotated Chinese Art Exhibition Catalogs, miscellaneous, 1920-1933 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Art Motifs & Travel Sketches, 1902-1936, Series 6:; (Box 5-6, 8; 1.4 linear feet)
  Bluemner defined many of his groups of sketches and notes as either "Travel Sketches" or "Art Motifs". Many of these were developed into themes for his paintings. The folder titles listed below are Bluemner's own titles and definitions, such as "Alley", "Central Port", or "House & Mountain." The most extensive motif found here is "Trees" consisting of sketches and notes on various types of trees, including notes on the compositional layout of trees in his paintings. Bluemner also had art motif files of travel sketches of various places, mostly of towns in New Jersey, where he lived, but also of Italy, which he visited in 1912. Additional sketches of these same places are found among other files of art motifs.
  There is a group of sketches Bluemner called "Mixed Themata." Other terms he used to label this same material are "Very Valuable" and "Vermilion Themata." The items found here are the same types of sketches as the rest of his motif files, and some are labeled as "copies." It appears from his notes, found among these items, that these sketches and notes were pulled from his files of motifs and reorganized, perhaps because they were of greater importance to him. They were sorted by Bluemner according to his own coding system or set of abbreviations.
  The files include pencil, charcoal, and colored sketches, most of which are heavily annotated with notes about color and composition. Other items found in the files may include newspaper clippings of images related to the motif, and original file tabs and file dividers which Bluemner created. Bluemner recorded the date and place on almost all of the sketches.
  Art motifs and travel sketches are arranged alphabetically by subject according to Bluemner's original arrangement. Most of the categories of material are preceded by an envelope, originally containing the items, on which Bluemner wrote a title for the contents, dates, and extensive notes. It is believed, based on these notes, that Bluemner rearranged these papers and removed certain items while he was preparing to give them to John Davis Hatch. Researchers should be aware that items are generally not in chronological order, and every attempt has been made to keep the pages in Bluemner's original order. This series has been scanned in its entirety.
  - "Alley," 1917-1936, (3 folders) (Box 5, Folder 3-5)
  - "Central Port," 1913-1936, (3 folders) (Box 5, Folder 6-8)
  - "Chimneys, Boats, Tanks," 1914-1936, (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 9-10)
  - "Flowers," 1917-1924 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - "Gable - Complex," 1914-1935, (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 12-13)
  - "Gable - Single," 1914-1936, (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 14-15)
  - "House & Mountain," 1918-1936 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Places (Box 5)
    - "Beattiestown," 1913-1914 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - "Blackwells," 1914 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - "Elizabeth," 1919-1934 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - "Hoboken," 1914 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - "Italy," 1912, (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 21-22)
    - "Lehnenburg," 1914-1915 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - "Montville," 1914-1915 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - "Patterson," 1913-1916 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - "Quincy," 1922-1926, (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 26-27)
    - "Rockaway," 1912-1916 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - "South River," 1913-1916 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - "Sparkhill," 1915-1916 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - "Stanhope," 1914-1916 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - "Wharton," 1913-1914 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - "Sky" & "Night" (also includes sketches of "Sun", "Moon", "Clouds"), 1910-1936, (5 folders) (Box 5, Folder 33-37)
  - "Snow Pictures," 1912-1933 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - "Square-Wall," 1913-1936, (3 folders) (Box 5, Folder 39-41)
  - Trees (Box 5)
    - "Tree analysis for painting," 1913-1933 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - "Trees in combination with other shapes," 1907-1926 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - "Altera Centre Setting," 1912-1935 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - "Woods" & "Shape of Foliage," 1914-1924 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - "Snow & Trees," 1926-1933 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - "Dome-Shaped Trees: Beech, Elm, Chestnut, Locust, Ash," 1902-1925 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - "Fruit Trees," 1917-1928 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - "Oak, Maple, Tulip, Dogwood," 1903-1933 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - "Pine, Cedar, Poplar, Birch," 1900-1924 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - "Willows," 1905-1930 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - "Tree Trunks," 1906-1936 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - [Leaves & Shrubs], circa 1910s-1930s (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - "Historical," 1920-1921 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - [Watercolor sketches], 1925-1926 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - "General Folio" (also includes "Old Trunks"), 1912-1936, (3 folders) (Box 6, Folder 14-16)
  - "Mixed Themata," 1910-1936, (11 folders; See also Box 8) (Box 6, Folder 17-27)
  - Envelopes originally containing sketches, circa 1930s (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - "Mixed Themata," 1910-1936, (Scanned with Box 6, F25) (Box 8 (sol))
- Artwork, 1892-circa 1930s, Series 7:; (Box 6; 4 folders)
  This series contains two pen and ink drawings by Bluemner of the Cottage at Woodmere, a house he designed, as well as other miscellaneous artwork including a small painting of the Pergamon Museum and an ink sketch of the Bronx Court House. Also found is a small sketchbook containing ink sketches and watercolors, believed to have belonged to Bluemner, and two figure drawings by a child with "Julie" written on them. Numerous sketches and artwork are found in Bluemner's diaries, writings and notes, and art motifs.
  This series has been scanned in its entirety.
  - Drawings by Bluemner, "Cottage at Woodmere," circa 1901 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Miscellaneous Artwork by Oscar Bluemner, 1892, 1903-circa 1930s (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Sketchbook, circa early-1900s (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Unidentified Drawings (Possibly by "Julie"), circa late-1800s (Box 6, Folder 32)
- Printed Material, 1906-1939, 1960, undated, Series 8:; (Box 6; 0.3 linear feet)
  Found here are exhibition catalogs and announcements for Bluemner's individual and group exhibitions, some of which are annotated with prices and other information. Also found are news clippings about Bluemner and friends, as well as a clippings file compiled by Bluemner containing images of palm trees and cacti. Additional clippings are found among his diaries, annotated books, other writings, and notes. This series also contains copies of the German language New York magazine Walhalla which include articles by Bluemner, as well as a booklet containing his self-published essay on art.
  Printed material is arranged by type of material and chronologically within each folder, followed by envelopes annotated by Bluemner which originally contained portions of this material. This series has been scanned in its entirety.
  - Exhibition Announcements & Catalogs, 1912-1939, 1960, (3 folders) (Box 6, Folder 33-35)
  - News Clippings, 1906, 1911-1938, (4 folders) (Box 6, Folder 36-39)
  - Undated News Clippings, circa 1911-1938 (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - News Clippings of Palm Trees & Cactuses, circa 1920s-1930s (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - Articles by Samuel A. Lewisohn, 1931, 1933, 1935 (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - Booklet by Bluemner, "What and When is Painting? To-day," 1929 (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - Press Release, 1938 (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - Walhalla Magazine, 1915-1916 (Box 6, Folder 45)
  - Magazines, circa 1910-1928 (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1913-1930, undated (Box 6, Folder 47)
  - Envelopes originally containing printed material, circa 1930s (Box 6, Folder 48)
- Photographs, 1891, 1903, circa 1930s, Series 9:; (Box 6; 5 folders)
  This series contains a small number of photographs including three photographs of buildings designed by Bluemner, several photographs of his artwork, and contact prints of his artwork and Bluemner.
  Photographs of artwork have not been scanned.
  - Photographs of Buildings Designed by Bluemner, 1891, 1903 (Box 6, Folder 49)
  - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1930s, (3 folders; not scanned) (Box 6, Folder 50-52)
  - Prints from Negative Strips, circa 1930s, (Includes 1 image of Oscar Bluemner; partially scanned) (Box 6, Folder 53)